let's move now to thread libraries so these are
libraries I mentioned this before that provide
to the programmer an API so some
facility to manipulate and to manage create
and destroy threads there are two ways of
course libraries that allow you to define
threads that should operate in user space and
others that can operate at the kernel level
pthreads is probably the most known
one common one in Unix systems at least
okay it provides both user level and kernel
level threads and what is important here is that
we're talking about a specification
not an implementation
depending on the system you use and the version
you use and the implementation you use of pthreads
you will have certain possibilities enabled
by the library some specific details about
how they behave and so on it's important
to make this distinction because you might ask
but if I called a specific
function like the one I show you
next what will I get and the answer to that
is it depends on which implementation you use
because we are looking at a specification not
at the implementation so let's have a look at
a simple example the example doesn't really
make sense in terms of using a multi-threaded
process because as you hopefully will understand
you don't really need to create two threads to do
this but this is just from let's say an educational
perspective so we want to sum all the numbers
between zero and n and n is a number that is
passed by the user and we want to create a
thread to do this instead of doing it with the
original thread with which the process starts
we create some global variable sum and
then we define here the function runner
and then we start with the main so we create
an id for the thread that we are going to create
and we also create attributes for the thread
this is because at the time when we will use
the pthreads to tell the operating system we
would like to create a new thread for this
process we are requested to pass some attribute
some information about how the thread should
be created we check the number of arguments
it needs to be two otherwise the program ends
and you know that the first one is the name of the
program so we actually have to pass one number if
we do we check whether the we can convert this
number to an integer and that that number is
greater or equal to zero otherwise we also return
then this is what we do so we use the library
to simplify our interaction with the
operating system and what we do is that we
create an initial setup for the attributes of the
thread we could manually specify them but if
we don't want we can just set the default
attributes and then we call pthread_create
so here we are telling to
the operating system that
through the library that we would like to
create a new thread that belongs to this process
that we would like the id of this new thread to
be stored here in the id of the thread that these
are the parameters the attributes for the thread
creation that when this thread starts it should
run the function called runner that we defined
before and that we want to pass to this function
what we have here which is the number that is
passed by the user so if this function runs
successfully when it's finished in our operating
system we will have this process with two threads
one thread will be the one that will run the next
instruction here so pthread_join the other thread
belonging to the same process will have its
program counter set to run runner okay so it
will start from this instruction now we have two
threads let's assume that these are kernel threads
okay for this example now this can be scheduled by
the operating system in different ways each
thread can run for a while can go in waiting can
be put back to ready there can be context switches
because of interrupts everything can happen okay
we don't know in which order is going to happen
so there is no guarantee that when the new
thread starts it will do everything and then exit
before the original thread will run the
next instruction so how do we synchronize
these threads because our final goal is to
print here the value of sum sum is a global
variable and since this is in the data section
of the process that is shared by all the threads
if one thread modifies it the other thread will
also see that the value has changed the problem
is that before we print it we need to be sure that
the other thread the new one that is running the
runner function has actually completed how do we
do this well the library gives us another function
pthread_join and we pass the id here and so what
we are telling now the operating system is that
we want this thread to stop its execution and go
into waiting and wait until there is a signal by
the operating system that tells to this thread
that the other thread the one that is running
the function runner has completed again we
don't know in which order threads will be executed
it might be that by the time this thread calls
pthread_join the other thread is already done
or not but it doesn't really matter the
important thing is that for sure by the time that
this thread wants to run print then the other
thread will be finished for sure because here we
force the execution to stop until the other thread
is finished so what the other thread does is the
following it creates some local variable it gets a
parameter it converts it to an integer
it sets 0 to sum sum is a global variable
is not a local one so these modifications
the modifications done on this variable will be
visible also for the other thread then it runs
the sum and it uses again the library to tell to
the operating system i'm done i'm finished and
everything went well this is why it's passing
value zero as I said before manual read the
specification of all these functions to understand
well what they're doing and even more now
we can create one thread or we can create a lot
of threads so we could
call the function pthread_create many times
and we would get if we call
it 10 times we would get a process with
10 plus one thread the original one plus
the 10 ones we create we can of course create
an array like here in which we keep
the ids of all the workers and if
we want to wait for all of them
before going on with our execution we can of
course do something like this so create a for loop
and then wait for each one of them to complete
again it might be that by the time we ask the
first one whether it has completed it has already
completed by the time we ask the second one that
has not completed it and we have to actually
wait by the time we ask the third one it has
completed and so on we don't know in which order
these things would be executed but we know for
sure that nothing will happen in the main thread
until all of them have completed their execution